All right.
In this lecture
we're going to talk about serverless
architectures in in cloud computing.
So leveraging both function as a service
PaaS solutions and self-hosted models.
So first off what is serverless.
It's kind of a misnomer because
people think oh it's not using servers.
It actually is using servers.
There are CPUs on the back end, but
it's abstracted everything away from you.
So, people call it function as a service.
It means I got a piece of code
and that's all I've got.
And all I have to do is submit something,
and that piece of code will start up
and take whatever input you gave it,
do its work, and then go away.
So that's the idea behind it.
Developers can deploy these individual
functions to do, little things.
And most of the cloud service providers
have this as a pay per use.
So every time it uses something
it kicks off and does something.
No servers are provisioned.
There are
you don't have to provision any servers.
There are servers provisioned.
There's a pool of servers on the back end
that are just being used
to run this code for you. Right.
So everything scales
automatically for you on the back end.
It just simplifies we've abstracted to the
to the smallest,
level that we possibly can,
which is a function to do something.
That's that's it.
Very simple. Very powerful tool.
So there's different execution models
that I can talk about
function as a service,
which you've already talked about.
The smallest granularity there.
It's all event driven.
So given an event run this function.
That's that's it.
Very simple.
Examples of this are AWS
Lambda, Azure Functions
and Google Cloud Functions,
which are options out there.
And then there's platform
as a service here
where the entire framework
has all the microservices in there.
It's still event driven, still has
it has that functionality.
But things like, AWS
elastic Beanstalk and App Engine
are these type of execution models
where it's more than just an individual
function, it's serverless still,
in that I am I'm starting up a service,
but I'm not starting up a server to run
a service on it, if that makes any sense.
And then there's self-hosted, frameworks,
like, fast frameworks, for example,
like open fast,
native and Apache open whisk.
So to two real
execution models that right functions
and then service.
Right.
I'm going to fire up a service
a service gets fired up
and the servers are automatically,
being scaled up and down for me.
So that's the main difference
between those.
All right.
Lots of different use cases.
If I have, a, a bunch of data
pipelining that I want to do,
or I have event processing that I want to
do, this is perfect for that.
Right?
Great example.
Let's say that, from a
the podcast that I do.
Right when I release, a new, podcast,
maybe I want to take that,
podcast video that I do, and I want to
chop it up into a bunch of small, shorts
that are every 15 seconds,
long of the whole thing.
Well, I could easily send
that on to a function as a service.
Hey, when a new podcast arrives, boom.
Break this thing up into.
And then I can have a function for each.
Each one of those, fire off.
Right. So great for those types of things.
Real time streaming and processing
is another great one.
We see this in, analytics
of large systems
where a certain event happens.
Security systems is a good one.
Scheduled tasks,
you know, anything like that?
A lot of really good integration points
you can use for functions of service type
things, things that use webhooks or bots,
that are generating events
that I want to capture
and then do something with.
So these are all great use cases
for, a fast function as a service or,
or even service, paths, platforms
that are firing up services for me.
A lot of advantages.
One of them is operational simplicity,
meaning
I don't have to manage the operations
side of things.
Automatic scaling is done for me.
It can be cost efficient.
If you are managing your events
appropriately, you're only going to pay
for, the use of, the service.
For the short period of time
that you're using,
things,
there are some gotchas here
you got to be careful of,
but we'll talk about that later.
But built in high
availability is already built
in, so it takes care of a lot of the
operational infrastructure on the back end
that you would normally have to do.
So it's a great platform.
For that.
Some disadvantages
when you first get started thing
there's some idle time, right,
to get things going because I've got,
automatically provisioned things.
You have to be
careful vendor lock in an AWS Lambda.
Incredible tool,
but you're locked into AWS Lambda.
There's no way around it. Right?
Using some of the open source tools
means you have to manage it,
some of that yourself, so you don't get
all the benefits you get from a CSP.
But the CSPs have not normalized these.
There's not a standard for function
as a service across the board.
And that brings, lock in. Right.
You also have to,
look at maximum timeout
on some of these, functions like Lambda.
There's a 15 minute timeout.
So if you think takes more than 15 minutes
at times out.
Anyway, so there's resource limitations
on these as well because they're
trying to reuse really cheap.
EC2 type instances.
Any really cheap, VMs out there.
They're going to use these
for these small function as a service.
So they're not great for big jobs,
but they're great for small little tiny
things.
They also are very difficult
very, very difficult to debug and monitor
because things are just happening
in an event driven way.
And it's hard to you can't really put
a debugger on these things.
Right.
So you've got to debug, parts separately.
But the whole system running is very hard
to, to monitor and see what's going on.
So those are some, some trade offs.
Okay.
Let's take a look at a fast,
like function as a service like Lambda.
Right. Great example.
Very easy to set up cold start impact
when you first get started.
It could be a little slow,
but once you get those first, instances
up and running, things, work pretty well,
and you get charged per
call on this one, right?
Very high lock in risk.
You got to be careful on the next one
if you're using a Paz.
Here, you know,
you've got more flexibility here.
Moderate. Management.
You can, you can, you can put containers
in ahead of time that warm things up.
You've got autoscale policies
that you have to manage.
You get charged per instance hours
instead of per call.
So if you have a lot of events,
this might be a cheaper way to go.
And most of the,
Paz platforms, can be portable.
I mean, if you're
if you're using some of the more open
source, platforms like Kubernetes
and things like that,
that's more portable
if you're going to host your own trials,
that's the most portable of all of them.
And,
there's, there's a couple platforms
out there that you can use,
and it does a pretty good job,
but you're still managing things yourself.
So, the cost model on this is,
you got to pay for your infrastructure.
If you're running it locally, then you've
already eaten that cost with your CapEx.
So, most portability,
self-hosted, least portability, fast,
easiest to use, fast, hardest
to use self-hosted.
Just like almost all the other things
that we've talked
about in these architectures.
All right.
So key considerations and best practices
around, using serverless
if you have, a new start,
if your programs are starting up,
be wise to start up costs. Right.
Starting up those VM starting up
those instances can take time.
So you may want to do a warm
start on that.
If you need to.
Also make sure that you have a stateless
design for these functions as a service.
If you're storing state,
you're going to have an issue, right?
Because you don't know when or where
these are running.
Right.
Make sure that you have centralized
logging for observability
on these functions that are out there.
Otherwise you could easily lose track of
what's going on out there.
There's great tools out there
like CloudWatch or Stackdriver
that that can do that.
Always practice
least privilege on your IAM
roles, network isolation,
secret management, all that stuff.
Still need to deal with that
with function as a service.
If you're doing anything with encryption
or you've got keys or certs,
you still need to deal with that.
And also look at your CI, CD pipeline,
for automating your builds and doing your
Bluegreen Canary deployments
just because you have a function,
it's a piece of code that you're
just injecting into, like the cloud.
You want to make sure
that you're doing all your normal CI, CD,
pipeline and quality before you go
and push that into production.
So don't forget those things.
All right?
When do you want to self-hosted?
When you've got strict data, compliance.
You're worried about vendor lock lock in.
You want to customize runtime
to maybe remember
the CCP's are going to use their cheapest,
oldest,
EC2 instances out there
because they want to monetize
those old resource.
So that's why they use this.
If you want to use certain
silicon features that are newer silicon,
then you want to, host your own there.
All right.
So be mindful of what's happening
on the back end of these things
and take advantage of self-hosting.
All right.
Identify your workloads.
Make sure that it fits an event
driven architecture.
Also you want to prototype some things
with some
maybe on some managed, like Lambda first
to see if it's going to work.
And then you can make a decision
to move off of it,
keep it very lightweight
on your prototyping.
Right.
Don't forget about the cold starts
and concurrency.
And that adds cost to things.
And explore
some of the hybrid managed, fast, self
self-hosted, solutions out there.
They can really give you an advantage,
especially if you're doing cloud
to edge architectures and FAS.
You really can't do that with Lambda
very well. So,
doing a self-hosted FAS
is probably the best way to go there.
And don't forget about it.
Survivability and security guardrails.
So that's it for serverless.